Mariano Riva Palacio Collection:
University of Texas at Austin
- Enero-Junio 1850
  - 4266 Jiménez, José María. Mexico, June 8, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for José Victoriano Martínez for position in Juzgado de Letras de Actopan; spread of the cholera; Otero.
  - 4267 Arróyabe, Lorenzo. Mexico, June 8, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Plans to purchase Hacienda de Panoaya; request for postponement of payment of the alcabala; Cortina; Landa. Includes draft of answer, June 11, with tentative offer, requiring approval of Rovalo; Chávez.
  - 4268 Navarro, Mariano. Jilotepec, June 8, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Dispatch of supply of raíz del indio; spread of the cholera; construction of jail; Fernando Batres; Salvador Batres; Hospital de San Juan de Dios; schools.
  - 4269 García, José María. Villa del Valle, June 8, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Meeting of the Junta de partido; spread of cholera from Michoacán.
  - 4270 Sein, A[ntonio]. Tula, June 8, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Spread of the epidemic; prisoners removed to the hospital; illness of priests; lack of spiritual aid; vicario foráneo de Actopan.
  - 4271 Valdés, Ramón F. Mexico, June 8, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    End of work as deputy to the Congreso General; abundance of lawyers in Mexico; request for position with the Tribunal Superior.
  - 4272 Herrera y Campos, Francisco. Texcoco, June 8, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request of Enrique de la Tijera for postponement of payment of alcabala on purchase of Hacienda de San Nicolás Mipuleo; ownership of store on corner of Jesús and Balvanera; spread of cholera in Municipalidad de Chimalhuacán.
  - 4273 León, Esteban V. Tem[]c, June 8, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Notice of disorders in Guanajuato; Calderón; Sultepec; Monte de la Cumbre; illness; attack on the Recaudador de Contribuciones de Amatepec; danger of disorder in San Andrés; uprising in 1849 led by Luis Zamudio; surveillance over Sultepec and Amatepec; Juan León; epidemic.
  - 4274 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, June 8, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letter-head.
    Death of Otero; news from Calderón.
  - 4275 Barrio, Juan N. del. Mexico, June 8, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Release of Medina from care of the road; effects of the cholera; Otero.
  - 4276 Ruano, Pedro. Temascaltepec, June 8, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Relief over recovery from illness.
  - 4277 Malo, José Ramón. Mexico, June 8, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Mackintosh case postponed pending recovery of Escudero; spread of the cholera; Manuel Portu; Bassoco; arrival of English packet; invasion of Cuba by American adventurers.
  - 4278 Velázquez, J. Francisco. Guadalupe, June 9, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm., 1 l. 16 × 21 cm.
    Payroll for Asunción; low price of corn; Juan Núñez; spread of the cholera; services of five doctors; druggists; medical supplies; request for more cemeteries; Tlalmanalco; San Gregorio; prohibition of food sales; Hacienda del Moral y San José; illness of Garrido; Zamora. Includes draft of answer, June 12, on sale of corn to López; cholera; office of subprefecto.
  - 4279 Villaseñor, Alejandro. Cuernavaca, June 9, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    State of the epidemic; death of Gavilán; concern for the future of his children.
  - 4280 Portilla, J. de la. Morelos, June 9, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for leave to visit ill family in Mexico; epidemic; reduction in number of prisoners.
  - 4281 Martínez, Primitivo. Chalco, June 9, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm., 1 l. 16 × 21 cm.
    State of the epidemic; danger to Mexico; objection to the capitation tax; hardship on poor classes; collection by commission from Texcoco; Colín. Includes draft of answer June 12, denying excessiveness of the tax of one real a month.
  - 4282 Cervantes, José J. Atenco, June 9, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Delivery of Raíz del indio; La Trouplinière; effects of the cholera. Includes note by José María Lebrija.
  - 4283 Herrera y Campos, Francisco. Texcoco, June 10, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Promulgation of regulations for sanitary measures; failure of local authorities to follow orders; conditions in Chimalhuacán and Papalotla; spread of the cholera; care of the ill; plans to discharge Castro in Chalco and Andonáegui in Teotihuacán; shortage of priests; Tlahuac; Texcoco.
  - 4284 Colín, José Nicolás E. de. Asunción, June 10, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Distribution of raíz del indio; Flores; Velázquez; Nopalera; hail damage to crops; Cuigingo; delivery of corn to Mier y Terán; Luis; Cadena; Julián; death of Abrahán Estévanez in Chalco; cholera.
  - 4285 Escudero, P[edro]. Mexico, June 10, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recovery from illness; reduced circumstances of family of Otero; sale of house on Calle de las Damas; spread of the cholera; Doloritas; Juzgado de Temascaltepec.
  - 4286 Linares, José María. [Carta a Vicente Riva Palacio.] Mexico, June 11, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 14 × 19 cm.
    Delivery of letters to El Siglo; comparison of teachers; Tepic; anecdote of the epidemic; Carlos.
  - 4287 Alcocer, Luis A. San Pablo, June 11, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Medicinal value of raíz del indio; advice of treatment of epidemic; suppression of news; secret burial; foods.
  - 4288 [Mier y Terán,] Gregorio. Mexico, June 11, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Payments to Juan de Dios Núñez; Ramón de la Cueva; Francisco Mendoza; houses on El Callejón de los Dolores, and Calle de la Concepción as security; Portal de Mercaderes; Barajas; Pepe; Revilla; Doloritas.
  - 4289 Villaurrutia, A. de. Mexico, June 11, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Receipt of raíz del indio; use in prison.
  - 4290 Cano, Anselmo. Mexico, June 11, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm., 1 l. 16 × 21 cm.
    Refusal of Indians of Almoloya to allow free flow of water of Huejocal to the Hacienda de Ocotepec; Quintana; appeal to the Juez de Apam; Guzmán. Includes draft of answer, June 15, offering help in enforcing the agreement.
  - 4291 Flores, Bernardo. Mexico, June 12, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for help in establishing a fund for the education of Otero's family and finding a house for their residence; help of Lacunza, Herrera, and Gómez Pedraza; Andresita.
  - 4292 Piedra, Epigmenio de la. Tenancingo, June 12, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Spread of the colera; opposition to prohibition on sale of liquor; gambling in private homes; Bernardo Quevedo.
  - 4293 Catalán, Prudencio. Tixtla de Guerrero, June 12, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Spread of the cholera; death of Goribar from cholera; Doloritas.
  - 4294 Pérez Palacios, Ángel. Cuernavaca, June 12, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Roads from Toluca to Ixtla and Cuernavaca to Morelos; spread of the cholera in Cuernavaca and Tetecala.
  - 4295 Lázaro, Obispo de Sonora. Culiacán, June 12, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Nomination to La mitra by the President.
  - 4296 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, June 12, 1850. LS. Printed letterhead., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Letter from León, warning of insurrection. Includes draft of answer, June 14, defending his policy.
  - 4297 Malo, José Ramón. Mexico, June 12, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Illness of Escudero; spread of the cholera; illness of Deputy from Querétaro Gervasio Irallo (?) and of Salvador Domínguez; Agustín.
  - 4298 Carrillo, L. Manuel. Mexico, June 12, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Support for Enrique de la Tijera.
  - 4299 Villasanto, Lino. Acambay, June 12, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Distribution of Yerba del indio; spread of the cholera; remedies.
  - 4300 Martel, Joaquín. Mexico, June 13, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Course of the water at El Molino de San Miguel changed by the police.
  - 4301 [Riva Palacio, Mariano.] [Tres borradores.] Toluca, June 14, 1850. Unsigned., 2 l. 16 × 21 cm.
    - a. [Borrador a José Joaquín de Herrera.] 1 l. f. 1. Request for scholarship to San Juan de Letrán for children of Otero.
    - b. [Borrador a José María Lacunza.] 1 l. f. 1. Scholarship at San Juan de Letrán for children of Otero.
    - c. [Borrador a Bernardo Flores.] 1 l. f. 2-2v. Request for copy of Otero's will; care of his children; Escudero; Herrera; Lacunza; Vicario capitular; Pedraza.
  - 4302 Pérez Palacios, Ángel. Cuernavaca, June 14, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Difficulty of road construction during the epidemic; Toluca-Ixtla road; Cuernavaca-Morelos Road; Luis [Pérez Palacios]; Aparicio; spread of the cholera; Hospital de Caridad; toll collection; Junta inspectora.
  - 4303 Calderón, Lorenzo. Sultepec, June 14, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Settlement of uprising in Guanajuato; role of Manuel Vélez of Tacámbaro in uprising against Bustamante in 1838-1839; collection of personal tax in Amatepec and Coatepec; Cañedo; epidemic; García Aguirre.
  - 4304 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, June 14, 1850. ALS. 2 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Note on illness; dispatch of troops to seize suspects; search for Ampudia; Tlalpa; agent of Perdigón sought in La Magdalena.
  - 4305 Cervantes, Miguel. Mexico, June 14, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Spread of the epidemic; renewal of bandit activity in Texcoco; El Salado; Oliveros; guards in Cerro Gordo; San Gregorio.
  - 4306 Iturbe, Francisco. Mexico, June 14, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Road construction in Tula area; railroad suggested; illness of Riva Palacio.
  - 4307 Estrada, Juan. Jalmolonga, June 14, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for recommendation to Juan Álvarez; appointment as Inspector del camino de Acapulco, Estado de Guerrero; Malinalco.
  - 4308 Thorn, James. [Carta a José Warmuth, Calle Cadenas, Mexico.] Acapulco, June 15, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 19 × 24 cm.
    Departure for California; commercial prospects; draft on Butterfield; sale of saddles; Señorita Corina; Simonsfeldt.
  - 4309 Almonte, Juan N. Mexico, June 15, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Ramón Francisco Valdés, applicant for position with Tribunal Superior.
  - 4310 [Noriega,] Joaquín. Mexico, June 15, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Illness; Antonio Herrera; spread of cholera; remedies; Mariquita; Mariana; Agustín; Doloritas.
  - 4311 Gorospe, Manuel M. Mexico, June 15, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for José G. de los Cobos for the Tribunal Superior.
  - 4312 Malo, José Ramón. Mexico, June 15, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Illness of Escudero; negotiations with MacKintosh; spread of cholera; Agustín [Díaz].
  - 4313 Madariaga, José María. Taxco, June 15, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Abandonment of public service recommended in favor of Madrid; medical advice; cholera in Taxco, Tetecala, and San Gabriel.
  - 4314 Rovalo, Luis. Mexico, June 15, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Spread of cholera; Santa Inés; accounts of Madrid and Malda; Ordenanzas de Bilbao.
  - 4315 Cervantes, José J. Atenco, June 16, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Spread of cholera; Ana; medical attention; Bernarda; José Manuel; Doloritas.
  - 4316 Millán, Joaquín. Tenancingo, June 16, 1850. LS., 1 l. 22 × 28 cm.
    Supply of Chaca (raíz del indio) from Zumpahuacán; spread of cholera; Luis G. García.
  - 4317 Villar, José del. Coyoacán, June 17, 1850. LS., 1 l. 22 × 28 cm.
    Spread of cholera; Ampudia; Pénjamo; Liciaga; Cañedo; Ortega.
  - 4318 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, June 17, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Capture of Cañedo's murderer.
  - 4319 Oliveros, Ignacio. Morelos, June 17, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Cholera in Santiago Tianguistenco.
  - 4320 Lacunza, [J. M.] Mexico, June 17, 1850. LS., 2 l. 20 × 25 cm.
    Scholarship provided for children of Otero; Eulalio Ortega; San Juan de Letrán; San Gregorio.
  - 4321 Zamora, Blas. Coatepec, June 17, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Cholera in Chimalhuacán, San Vicente, Coatepec, Ixtapaluca, Ayotla, Tlapacoya[n], Mizquique; remedies; receta de Muñoz; Doloritas.
  - 4322 Castañeda, Marcelino. Mexico, June 17, 1850. ALS. 2 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead of Ministro de Justicia.
    Capture of Cañedo's assassin; Cuartel de Mina; León; illness. Includes draft of answer, sharing pleasure in the capture.
  - 4323 Otero, Andrea A. de. Mexico, June 18, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Appointment of Pedraza and Riva Palacio as executors of Otero's estate; Escudero.
  - 4324 Noriega, A[gustín]. Mexico, June 18, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Reports of removal of archives by Joaquín Pérez Tejada; withdrawal to Tlalnepantla and Cuautitlán on account of illness; opposition to the change; Junta de Caridad; cholera; remedies; illness of niece; Mariana; Joaquín; Pepe; Doloritas.
  - 4325 Azcárate, Miguel María. Gobierno del Distrito Federal, Mexico, June 18, 1850. LS. 2 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Drunkenness of hangsman; use of substitute. Includes draft of answer, concerning use of executioner at Tlalpam.
  - 4326 Villaseñor, Juan N. María. Texcalyacac, June 19, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for intervention with Cura de la capital for help in spiritual services to victims of cholera; illness of two priests.
  - 4327 Herrera, José Joaquín de. Mexico, June 19, 1850. ALS. 2 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Capture of Cañedo's assassin; illness.
  - 4328 Sánchez Solís, Felipe. June 19, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Teófilo Sánchez for Juzgado de Letras.
  - 4329 Rovalo, Luis. Mexico, June 19, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Bill sent to Madrid by Ruiz; Malda; capture of assassin of Cañedo; spread of the cholera in San Gabriel, Temisco, and San Carlos; report of Barrio.
  - 4330 Haro y Tamariz, Antonio de. Mexico, June 19, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Newspaper reports of Riva's health; recommendation for Valdez; Mier y Terán; Doloritas.
  - 4331 Malo, José Ramón. Mexico, June 19, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Illness of Escudero; the MacKintosh negotiations; Juzgado de Circuito; spread of the cholera; illness of Echeverría (nephew of Riva Palacio); Agustín; Joaquín; night burials; Luis de Veyra (?).
  - 4332 Colín, José Nicolás E. de. Asunción, June 19, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Letters for Velázquez and Gómez; Flores; Primitivo; interview with Gregorio de Mier y Terán requested by Barajas; crop at San Juan de Dios; Juan Estrada; cholera; remedies; raíz del indio; Tula; Tejocote; wheat crop; Nopalera; Luis; Cadena; Julián; bean crop.
  - 4333 Andrade, Cristóbal, Zacualtipán, June 20, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Departure for Metztitlán; opposition to payment of the personal tax; support of Administrador de Zacualtipán; Consejos de salubridad; danger of the cholera; shortage of doctors.
  - 4334 Romero, José María. Tenancingo, June 20, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Thanks for help in obtaining back pay.
  - 4335 Solórzano, Mariano. Tenancingo, June 20, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Refusal of appointment as Fiscal sustituto del Tribunal Superior; help of Cruz and Pérez Fernández; plea of ill health.
  - 4336 Daza y Argüelles, Antonio. Hacienda de Guadalupe, June 20, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for aid in obtaining compliance with order suspending collection of alcabala for sale of Hacienda de Guadalupe de los Nogales by Señora Ordieres; Cura del Mineral del Chico Mariano Monterde; Juzgado de Letras de Metztitlán; appeal to Ministro Castañeda and Couto; Aguirre.
  - 4337 Villamil, Gerónimo. Tezontlalpa, June 20, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Transmittal of complaint; request for aid in obtaining justice.
  - 4338 Cervantes, José J. Atenco, June 20, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Progress of the cholera; illness of Lola; capture of assassin of Cañedo; Doloritas; Ana; Bernarda; José Manuel.
  - 4339 Herrera y Campos, Francisco. Texcoco, June 20, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Apathy of the public toward sanitary measures; inactivity of the government officers; appointment of Velázquez in Chalco; replacements needed in Teotihuacán and Otumba; loss of confidence in Andonáegui; collection of tax on the haciendas; provisions for meeting the cholera; dispersal of the Ayuntamiento in Chimalhuacán; Junta de Caridad; improved organization in Chicoloapam; remedies; raíz del indio; Tijera; Rebollar; Tonchita; birth of daughter María Antonia de la Luz; Juliana.
  - 4340 Calderón, Lorenzo. Sultepec, June 21, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Report on cholera; meeting with Lic. Alas; Presbítero Manuel Campozano; José María Mariano Campozano; peacefulness of the Partido; Zacualpam.
  - 4341 Gorospe, Manuel M. Mexico, June 21, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for leave for Javier Lagarde; death of wife in Tula from cholera.
  - 4342 [Noriega,] Joaquín. Mexico, June 21, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Death of Doloritas, daughter of Mariana; spread of the cholera; Romero; Aguirre; illness of Aramburu.
  - 4343 Lozano, José María. Mexico, June 21, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Death of Ignacio Flores from cholera; concern for his family; death of Francisco Rodríguez; death of a student of the college; Barajas; illness of Riva Palacio.
  - 4344 Pérez Palacios, Ángel. Cuernavaca, June 21, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Theft of mules by robber band; flight to Tlatlaco(?); spread of cholera.
  - 4345 Terreros, Manuel. Mexico, June 21, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for aid in obtaining justice for uncle, Gerónimo Villamil; Recaudador Ortega; difficulties of Ortega in collecting personal tax.
  - 4346 Sein, A[ntonio]. Tula, June 22, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for priests; suspension of Alejandro Garrido from Subprefectura de Zimapán; Jacala; desertion of courier in Mexico; progress of the cholera; illness of Administrador de Rentas Pérez.
  - 4347 Villar, José del. Coyoacán, June 22, 1850. LS., 2 l. 22 × 28 cm.
    Progress of the cholera; deaths in San Ángel; remedies; el método de Vázquez; order for execution of the González; execution of Francisco González; Ignacio Cortina Chávez; death of Ignacio Flores; Mier; Noriega; death of Pedro [González] of cholera.
  - 4348 León, Esteban V. Temascaltepec, June 22, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Departure for Zacualpam; financial claim of the Administrador; request for pay for soldiers; capture of José María Áviles; progress of the cholera; letters from Santa Anna found in hands of officers; Cuba; officers invited to Mexico.
  - 4349 Robles, Manuel. Cuerpo Nacional de Ingenieros, Veracruz, June 22, 1850. LS. 1 l. 20 × 25 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Acknowledgement of decree naming him honorary citizen of the State of Mexico.
  - 4350 Malo, José Ramón. Mexico, June 22, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Illness of Escudero; Agustín; progress of the cholera; report of deaths.
  - 4351 Gálvez, Mariano (Martín?). Mexico, June 23, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Flood on the Río Churubusco; increase in cholera; apathy of the Juez de paz; request for help.
  - 4352 Viadas, J. Mariano. Tehuacán, June 24, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for intervention in the case of a fine levied on his brother, Juan María, by Alejandro Villaseñor as Prefecto for not keeping his pharmacy shop open; health conditions in the city.
  - 4353 Eguiarte, Agustín G. Mexico, June 24, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for extension of leave; study of title papers of Hacienda de San Nicolás Peralta and Hacienda de Doña Rosa; epidemic.
  - 4354 Jiménez, José María. Mexico, June 25, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Francisco Inclán, Juez de Letras de Huamantla; request for transfer to another juzgado for the benefit of his wife's health.
  - 4355 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, June 25, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Rumors of a pending uprising near Toluca; ammunition supplied from Mexico by Pío Marcha.
  - 4356 Lagarde y Gassín, Javier. Tula, June 25, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Complaint against the Prefecto; death of wife; Tlalnepantla; defense of his actions.
  - 4357 Garrido, A. Zimapán, June 26, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Service as diputado in 1845 with Robledo; protest against replacement by Sein in the Subprefectura; cholera.
  - 4358 Barreira, Eug[eni] o Z. Mexico, June 26, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Need for blankets during the epidemic; offer to sell one thousand at 17 reales each.
  - 4359 Villaseñor, Alejandro. Cuernavaca, June 26, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Death of son Ricardo from cholera; illness of son Gregorio; medical attention; illness of Pepita.
  - 4360 Catalán, Prudencio. Tixtla, June 26, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Death of Agustín Pérez Gavilán in Tetecala; care of his family; Sister Feliciana; Doloritas.
  - 4361 Gómez, J. F. Guerrero, June 26, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Spread of cholera in Ciudad Guerrero, Iguala, District of Taxco, Teloloapa[n], and Ajuchitlán; movement toward Acapulco; shortage of doctors; notices in La Aurora; adjournment of legislature in face of the epidemic; lack of courts; formation of padrones suspended on account of the cholera.
  - 4362 Zasaya de Rodríguez, Dolores. Mexico, June 26, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Personal problems caused by death of Flores; Cumplido; Francisco Rodríguez.
  - 4363 Solórzano, Mariano. Tenancingo, June 26, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Appointment to Tribunal Superior declined because of cholera in Toluca.
  - 4364 Malo, José Ramón. Mexico, June 26, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Illness of Escudero; progress of cholera; death of Sierra of the Corte de Justicia, José de Garay and sons, Parra of Ministerio de Relaciones; anticipated resignation of Bonifacio Gutiérrez; problems of medical care in hospitals; Agustín; Marianita.
  - 4365 Rovalo, Luis. Mexico, June 26, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Delivery of mail to Madrid; female office help; José Juan; progress of cholera; death of José María Garay and sons.
  - 4366 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, June 26, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Plan for use of prisoners to work on roads between Veracruz and Acapulco; approval of Álvarez; cholera.
  - 4367 Couto, Bernardo. Mexico, June 26, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for a friend; progress of cholera.
  - 4368 Pliego, Julio. Tiang[uisten]co, June 26, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Inability to carry on business during epidemic; need for priests; Cura Carrillo.
  - 4369 Cervantes, José J. Atenco, June 26, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Death of Sebastián Blanco; José Manuel; Antonio Ortiz; cholera in Atenco, Santiago, and Capul[h]uac; remedies; Doloritas.
  - 4369A Bernal, Patricio del. Postmarked June 26, [1850.] LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Gambling in Tulancingo; Segunda Calle Nacional; mesón del Ángel; house of Colonel D. B. J. L. LL.; high stakes; increase in industry; players from Distrito Federal in Pachuca; beginning of cholera; corruption of youths.
  - 4370 Garay, Antonio. Mexico, June 27, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Sale of Mina de Santa María, iron mine, by Josefina Faure to Aristeo Mairet; request for relief from paying the alcabala. Includes draft of answer, on reports from Tulancingo and Zacualpan.
  - 4371 Granados de Medina, Francisco. Teloloapan, June 27, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 30 cm.
    Request for position as judge; vacancy in Tetecala; progress of the cholera; use of raíz del indio; recipe for fumigating houses.
  - 4372 Villagrán, Rafael María. Huichapan, June 27, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Progress of the cholera in Actopan, Ixmiquilpan, and Tecozautla.
  - 4373 [Un observador de lo que pasa en el suyo.] Tepotzotlán, June 27, 1850. Unsigned., 1 l. 16 × 21 cm.
    Cholera; confusion in meat supply; poor quality of bread; Síndico Procurador blamed; lack of police protection.
  - 4374 González de la Vega, Pedro. Huichapan, June 27, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Preparation of title papers for Magos, Guadalupe Guerrero, and María Balzategui(?); Jilotepec.
  - 4375 Mata, José Manuel de. San Felipe, June 28, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.